<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE group [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<group from="2.1.4" to="2.1.5">
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishd</name>
    <change type="bug" ref="801">
      <para>On pass from vcl_recv, we did not remove the backends Content-Length
      header before adding our own. This could cause confusion for
      browsers and has been fixed.</para>
    </change>
   
    <change type="bug" ref="806">
      <para>Make pass with content-length work again. An issue with regards
      to 304, Content-Length and pass has been resolved.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="803">
      <para>An issue relating to passed requests with If-Modified-Since
      headers has been fixed. Varnish did not recognize that the
      304-response did not have a body.</para>
    </change>
   
    <change type="bug">
      <para>A potential lock-inversion with the ban lurker thread has been
      resolved.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Several build-dependency issues relating to rst2man have been
      fixed. Varnish should now build from source without rst2man if you
      are using tar-balls.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="780">
      <para>Ensure Varnish reads the expected last CRLF after chunked data
      from the backend. This allows re-use of the connection.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Remove a GNU Make-ism during <code>make dist</code> to make BSD
      happier.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Document the log, set, unset, return and restart statements in
      the VCL documentation.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="808">
      <para>Fix an embarrassingly old bug where Varnish would run out of
      workspace when requests come in fast over a single connection,
      typically during synthetic benchmarks.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="795">
      <para>Varnish will now allow <code>If-Modified-Since</code> requests
      to objects without a <code>Last-Modified</code>-header, and instead
      use the time the object was cached instead.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="789">
      <para>Do not filter out <code>Content-Range</code> headers in
      pass.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Require -d, -b, -f, -S or -T when starting Varnishd. In human
      terms, this means that it is legal to start varnishd without a Vcl or
      backend, but only if you have a CLI channel of some kind.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Don't suppress <code>Cache-Control</code> headers in pass
      responses.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Merge multi-line Cache-Control and Vary header fields. Until
      now, no browsers have needed this, but Chromium seems to find it
      necessary to spread its Cache-Control across two lines, and we get to
      deal with it.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="812">
      <para>Make new-purge not touch busy objects. This fixes a potential
      crash when calling <code>VRT_purge</code>.</para>
    </change>
    
    <change type="enh">
      <para>If there are everal grace-able objects, pick the least expired
      one.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="817">
      <para>Fix an issue with <code>varnishadm -T :6082</code>
      shorthand.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add bourn-shell like "here" documents on the CLI. Typical
      usage:
      <code>
      vcl.inline vcl_new << 42
      backend foo {...}
      sub vcl_recv {...}
      42
      </code></para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add CLI version to the CLI-banner, starting with version 1.0 to
      mark here-documents.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Fix a problem with the expiry thread slacking off during high
      load.</para>
    </change>

  </subsystem>

  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishtest</name>
    <change type="bug" ref="804">
      <para>Remove no longer existing <code>-L</code> option.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>


</group>
