<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE group [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<group from="2.0.6" to="2.1.0">
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishd</name>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Persistent storage is now experimentally supported using
      the <code>persistent</code> stevedore.  It has the same command
      line arguments as the file stevedore.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>obj.*</code> is now called <code>beresp.*</code>
      in <code>vcl_fetch</code>, and <code>obj.*</code> is now
      read-only.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>The regular expression engine is now PCRE instead of POSIX
      regular expressions.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>req.*</code> is now available
      in <code>vcl_deliver</code>.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add saint mode where we can attempt to grace an object if
	we don't like the backend response for some reason.</para>

      <para>Related, add <code>saintmode_threshold</code> which is the
	threshold for the number of objects to be added to the trouble
	list before the backend is considered sick.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add a new hashing method called critbit.  This autoscales
      and should work better on large object workloads than the
      classic hash.  Critbit has been made the default hash algorithm.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>When closing connections, we experimented with sending RST
      to free up load balancers and free up threads more quickly.
      This caused some problems with NAT routers and so has been
      reverted for now.
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add thread that checks objects against ban list in order
	to prevent ban list from growing forever.  Note that this
	needs purges to be written so they don't depend
	on <code>req.*</code>.  Enabled by
	setting <code>ban_lurker_sleep</code> to a nonzero
	value.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>The shared memory log file format was limited to maximum
      64k simultaneous connections.  This is now a 32 bit field which
      removes this limitation.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Remove obj_workspace, this is now sized automatically.
	</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Rename acceptors to waiters</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>vcl_prefetch</code> has been removed.  It was never
      fully implemented.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add support for authenticating CLI connections.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add hash director that chooses which backend to use
      depending on <code>req.hash</code>.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add client director that chooses which backend to use
      depending on the client's IP address.  Note that this ignores
      the <code>X-Forwarded-For</code> header.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>varnishd</code> now displays a banner by default
      when you connect to the CLI.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Increase performance somewhat by moving statistics
	gathering into a per-worker structure that is regularly
	flushed to the global stats.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Make sure we store the header and body of object together.
	This may in some cases improve performance and is needed for
	persistence.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Remove client-side address accounting.  It was never used
      for anything and presented a performance problem.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add a timestamp to bans, so you can know how old they are.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Quite a few people got confused over the warning about not
	being able to lock the shared memory log into RAM, so stop
	warning about that.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="329">
      <para>Change the default CLI timeout to 10 seconds.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="444">
      <para>We previously forced all inserts into the cache to be GET
	requests.  This has been changed to allow POST as well in
	order to be able to implement purge-on-POST semantics.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>The CLI command <code>stats</code> now only lists non-zero
	values.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>The CLI command <code>stats</code> now only lists non-zero
	values.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Use <code>daemon(3)</code> from <code>libcompat</code> on
	Darwin.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Remove <code>vcl_discard</code> as it causes too much
	complexity and never actually worked particularly well.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Remove <code>vcl_timeout</code> as it causes too much
	complexity and never actually worked particularly well.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Update the documentation so it refers
      to <code>sess_workspace</code>, not <code>http_workspace</code>.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Document the <code>-i</code> switch
      to <code>varnishd</code> as well as
      the <code>server.identity</code>
      and <code>server.hostname</code> VCL variables.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>purge.hash</code> is now deprecated and no longer
      shown in help listings.</code>.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="607">
      <para>When processing ESI, replace the five mandatory XML
      entities when we encounter them.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add string representations of time and relative
	time.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="604">
      <para>Add locking for <code>n_vbe_conn</code> to make it stop
      underflowing.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="207">
      <para>When ESI-processing content, check for illegal XML
      character entities.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="207">
      <para>Varnish can now connect its CLI to a remote instance when
      starting up, rather than just being connected to.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>It is no longer needed to specify the maximum number of
	HTTP headers to allow from backends.  This is now a run-time
	parameter.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="601, 540">
      <para>The <code>X-Forwarded-For</code> header is now generated
      by <code>vcl_recv</code> rather than the C code.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>It is now possible to not send all CLI traffic to
	syslog.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>It is now possible to not send all CLI traffic to
	syslog.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>In the case of varnish crashing, it now outputs a
      identifying string with the OS, OS revision, architecture and
      storage parameters together with the backtrace.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Use exponential backoff when we run out of file
	descriptors or sessions.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="635">
      <para>Allow setting backend timeouts to zero.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Count uptime in the shared memory log.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="620">
      <para>Try to detect the case of two running varnishes with the
      same shmlog and storage by writing the master and child process
      ids to the shmlog and refusing to start if they are still
      running.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="524">
      <para>Make sure to use EOF mode when serving ESI content to
	HTTP/1.0 clients.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="495">
      <para>Make sure we close the connection if it either
	sends <code>Connection: close</code> or it is a HTTP/1.0
	backend that does not send <code>Connection:
	keep-alive</code>.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Increase the default session workspace to 64k on 64-bit
	systems.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="644">
      <para>Make the <code>epoll</code> waiter use level triggering,
      not edge triggering as edge triggering caused problems on very
      busy servers.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="626">
      <para>Handle unforeseen client disconnections better on Solaris.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Make session lingering apply to new sessions, not just
      reused sessions.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishstat</name>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Make use of the new uptime field in the shared memory log
      rather than synthesizing it from the start time.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishlog</name>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Exit at the end of the file when started
	with <code>-d</code>.</para>
    </change>


varnishadm:
 - timeout support
 - secret support
 - handle cli banner

</group>
