<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE group [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<!-- $Id: changes-2.0.6-2.1.0.xml 4672 2010-04-19 10:26:23Z tfheen $ -->
<group from="2.0.6" to="2.1.0">
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishd</name>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>The changelog in 2.1.0 included syntax errors, causing
      the generated changelog to be empty.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>The help text for <code>default_grace</code> was wrongly
      formatted and included a syntax error.  This has now been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para><code>varnishd</code> now closes the file descriptor used
      to read the management secret file (from the <code>-S</code>
      parameter).</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="669">
      <para>The child would previously try to close every valid file
	descriptor, something which could cause problems if the file
	descriptor ulimit was set too high.  We now keep track of all
	the file descriptors we open and only close up to that number.
	</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>ESI was partially broken in 2.1.0 due to a bug in the
      rollback of session workspace.  This has been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Reject the <code>auth</code>command rather than crash if
      there is no <code>-S</code> parameter given.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Align pointers in allocated objects.  This will in theory
      make Varnish a tiny bit faster at the expense of slightly more
      memory usage.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Ensure the master process process id is updated in the
      shared memory log file after we go into the background.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" id="679">
      <para><code>HEAD</code> requests would be converted to GET
      requests too early, which affected <code>pass</code>
      and <code>pipe</code>.  This has been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Update the documentation to point out that the TTL is no
      longer taken into account to decide whether an object is
      cacheable or not.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add support for completely obliterating an object and all
      variants of it.  Currently, this has to be done using inline C.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add experimental support for the <code>Range</code>
      header.  This has to be enabled using the parameter
      http_range_support.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishsizes</name>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>varnishsizes</code>, which is
      like <code>varnishhost</code>, but for the length of objects,
      has been added..</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>
</group>
