<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE group [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<group from="2.1.3" to="2.1.4">
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishd</name>
    <change type="bug">
      <para>An embarrasing typo in the new binary heap layout caused
      inflated obj/objcore/objhdr counts and could cause odd problems
      when the LRU expunge mechanism was invoked.  This has been
      fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>We now have updated documentation in the reStructuredText
      format.  Manual pages and reference documentation are both built
      from this.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>We now include a DNS director which uses DNS for choosing
      which backend to route requests to.  Please see the
      documentation for more details.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="758">
      <para>If you restarted a request, the HTTP header
      <code>X-Forwarded-For</code> would be updated multiple times.
      This has been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="742">
      <para>If a VCL contained a % sign, and the <code>vcl.show</code>
      CLI command was used, varnishd would crash.  This has been
      fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="730">
      <para>When doing a pass operation, we would remove the
      <code>Content-Length</code>, <code>Age</code> and
      <code>Proxy-Auth</code> headers.  We are no longer doing
      this.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>now</code> has a string representation, making it
      easier to construct <code>Expires</code> headers in VCL.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="739">
      <para>In a high traffic environment, we would sometimes reuse a
      file descriptor before flushing the logs from a worker thread to
      the shared log buffer.  This would cause confusion in some of
      the tools.  This has been fixed by explicitly flushing the log
      when a backend connection is closed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="744">
      <para>If the communication between the management and the child
      process gets out of sync, we have no way to recover.
      Previously, <code>varnishd</code> would be confused, but we now
      just kill the child and restart it.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="479">
      <para>If the backend closes the connection on us just as we sent
      a request to it, we retry the request.  This should solve some
      interoperability problems with Apache and the mpm-itk multi
      processing module.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>varnishd</code> now only provides help output the
      current CLI session is authenticated for.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="733">
      <para>If the backend does not tell us which length indication it
      is using, we now assume the resource ends EOF at.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>The client director now has a variable
      <code>client.identity</code> which is used to choose which
      backend should receive a given request.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>The Solaris <code>port</code> waiter has been updated, and
      other portability fixes for Solaris.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="746">
      <para>There was a corner case in the close-down processing of pipes, this has now been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Previously, if we stopped polling a backend which was
      sick, it never got marked as healthy.  This has now been
      changed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>It is now possible to specify ports as part of the <code>.host</code> field in VCL.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="768">
      <para>The synthetic counters were not locked properly, and so
      the <code>sms_</code> counters could underflow.  This has now
      been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="769">
      <para>The value of <code>obj.status</code> as a string in vcl_error would not be correct in all cases.  This has been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="776">
      <para>Varnish would try to trim storage segments completely
      filled when using the malloc stevedore and the object was
      received chunked encoding.  This has been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="763">
      <para>If a buggy backend sends us a <code>Vary</code> header
      with two colons, we would previously abort.  We now rather fix
      this up and ignore the extra colon.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>req.hash_always_miss</code> and
      <code>req.hash_ignore_busy</code> has been added, to make
      preloading or periodically refreshing content work better.</para>
    </change>

  </subsystem>
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishncsa</name>
    <change type="bug">
      <para><code>varnishncsa</code> would in some cases be confused
      by ESI requests and output invalid lines.  This has now been
      fixed.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>

  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishlog</name>
    <change type="enh">
      <para><code>varnishlog</code> now allows <code>-o</code> and <code>-u</code> together.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>

  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishtop</name>
    <change type="bug">
      <para><code>varnishtop</code> would crash on 32 bit
      architectures.  This has been fixed.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>

  <subsystem>
    <name>libvarnishapi</name>
    <change type="bug">
      <para>Regex inclusion and exclusion had problems with matching
      particular parts of the string being matched.  This has been
      fixed.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>

</group>
