<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE group [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<group from="1.1" to="1.1.1">
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishd</name>

    <change type="bug" ref="1745">
      <para>The code required to allow VCL to read
      <code>obj.status</code>, which had accidentally been left out,
      has now been added.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1750">
      <para>Varnish will now always include a <code>Connection:</code>
      header in its reply to the client, to avoid possible
      misunderstandings.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="buf" ref="1751">
      <para>A bug that triggered an assertion failure when generating
      synthetic error documents has been corrected.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="1761,1762,1765,1828">
      <para>A new VCL function, <code>purge_url</code>, provides the
      same functionality as the <code>url.purge</code> management
      command.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="1780">
      <para>Previously, Varnish assumed that the response body should
      be sent only if the request method was <code>GET</code>.  This
      was a problem for custom request methods (such as
      <code>PURGE</code>), so the logic has been changed to always
      send the response body except in the specific case of a
      <code>HEAD</code> request.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1795">
      <para>Changes to run-time parameters are now correctly
      propagated to the child process.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1797">
      <para>Due to the way run-time parameters are initialized at
      startup, <code>varnishd</code> previously required the
      <code>nobody</code> user and the <code>nogroup</code> group to
      exist even if a different user and group were specified on the
      command line.  This has been corrected.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1800">
      <para>Under certain conditions, the VCL compiler would carry on
      after a syntax error instead of exiting after reporting the
      error.  This has been corrected.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="1803-1806">
      <para>The manner in which the hash string is assembled has been
      modified to reduce memory usage and memory-to-memory
      copying.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1807">
      <para>Before calling <code>vcl_miss</code>, Varnish assembles a
      tentative request object for the backend request which will
      usually follow.  This object would be leaked if
      <code>vcl_miss</code> returned anything else than
      <code>fetch</code>.  This has been corrected.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1808">
      <para>The code necessary to handle an <code>error</code> return
      from <code>vcl_fetch</code> and <code>vcl_deliver</code> had
      inadvertantly been left out.  This has been corrected.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1810">
      <para>Varnish no longer prints a spurious "child died" message
      (the result of reaping the compiler process) after compiling a
      new VCL configuration.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1838">
      <para>Under some circumstances, due to an error in the workspace
      management code, Varnish would lose the "tail" of a request,
      i.e. the part of the request that has been received from the
      client but not yet processed.  The most obvious symptom of this
      was that POST requests would work with some browsers but not
      others, depending on details of the browser's HTTP
      implementation.  This has been corrected.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="1855,1859">
      <para>On some platforms, due to incorrect assumptions in the CLI
      code, the management process would crash while processing
      commands received over the management port.  This has been
      corrected.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>

  <subsystem>
    <name>Build system</name>

    <change type="bug" ref="1752">
      <para>The top-level Makefile will now honor
      <code>$DESTDIR</code> when creating the state directory.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="1743,1846">
      <para>The Debian and RedHat packages are now split into three
      (main / lib / devel) as is customary.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="1753,1754,1783-1791,1798,1823,1794">
      <para>A number of compile-time and run-time portability issues
      have been addressed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="1811">
      <para>The <code>autogen.sh</code> script had workarounds for
      problems with the GNU autotools on FreeBSD; these are no longer
      needed and have been removed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh" ref="1817">
      <para>The <code>libcompat</code> library has been renamed to
      <code>libvarnishcompat</code> and is now dynamic rather than
      static.  This simplifies the build process and resolves an issue
      with the Mac OS X linker.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>
</group>
