<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE group [
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<group from="2.0.3" to="2.0.4">
  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishd</name>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Make Varnish more portable by pulling in fixes for
      Solaris and NetBSD.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Correct description of -a in the manual page.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>Ensure we are compiling in C99 mode.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="458">
      <para>If error was called with a null reason, we would crash on
      Solaris.  Make sure this no longer happens.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="428">
      <para>Varnish used to crash if you asked it to use a
      non-existent waiter.  This has now been fixed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add documentation to the default VCL explaining that
      using <code>Connection: close</code> in <code>vcl_close</code>
      is generally a good idea.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Add minimal facility for dealing with TELNET option
	negotiation by returning WONT to DO and DONT requests.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>If the backend is unhealthy, use a graced object if one is
      available.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Make <code>server.hostname</code>
      and <code>server.identity</code> available to VCL.  The latter
      can be set with the <code>-i</code> parameter
      to <code>varnishd</code>.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Make <code>restart</code> available
      from <code>vcl_error</code>.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Previously, only the TTL of an object was considered in
      whether it would be marked as cacheable.  This has been changed
      to take the grace into consideration as well.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug" ref="445">
      <para>Previously, if an included ESI fragment had a zero size,
      we would send out a zero-sized chunk which signifies
      end-of-transmission.  We now ignore zero-sized chunks.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="bug">
      <para>We accidentially slept for far too long when we reached
      the maximum number of open file descriptors.  This has been
      corrected and <code>accept_fd_holdoff</code> now works
      correctly.</para>
    </change>
    <change type="bug" ref="476">
      <para>Previously, when ESI processing, we did not look at the
      full length, but stopped at the first NULL byte.  We no longer
      do that, enabling ESI processing of binary data.</para>
    </change>

  <subsystem>
    <name>varnishtest</name>
    <change type="bug">
      <para>Make sure system "..." returns successfully to ensure
      test failures do not go unnoticed.</para>
    </change>

    <change type="enh">
      <para>Make it possible to send NULL bytes through the testing
      framework.</para>
    </change>
  </subsystem>
</group>
